<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties gracious speech to both houses of Parliament, on Wednesday, February the 18th. 1662. Being the first day of their meeting after their prorogation.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3048A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53298991</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53298991</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2802:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties gracious speech to both houses of Parliament, on Wednesday, February the 18th. 1662. Being the first day of their meeting after their prorogation.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Re-printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette: royal seal and initials "C.R."</note>
                  <note>Text in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Sources</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179768:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:179768:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
            <p>His Majeſties GRACIOUS SPEECH To both HOUSES of PARLIAMENT, <hi>On Wedneſday,</hi> February <hi>the</hi> 18. 1662. Being the firſt day of their meeting after their Prorogation.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Re-printed at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:179768:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179768:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
            <head>His <hi>Majeſties</hi>-Gracious SPEECH to both Houſes of Parliament, on <date>VVedneſday <hi>February</hi> the 18. 1662.</date> Being the firſt day of their meeting after their Prorogation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very glad to meet you here again, having thought the time long ſince We parted, and often wiſhed you had been to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to help Me in ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions which have fallen out; I need not repeat them unto you, you have all had the noiſe of them in your ſeveral Countries, and (God be thanked) they were but noiſe without any worſe effects.</p>
            <p>To cure the diſtempers, and compoſe the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering minds that are yet among Vs, I ſet forth my Declaration of the 26. of <hi>December,</hi> in which you may ſee I am willing to ſet bounds to the hopes of ſome, and to the fears of others; of which, when you ſhall have examined well the grounds, I doubt not but I ſhall have your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence therein: The truth is, I am, in my nature, an enemy to all ſeverity for Religion and Conſcience, how miſtaken ſoever it be, when it extends to capital and ſanguinary Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, which I am told were begun in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh times; therefore, when I ſay this, I hope I ſhall not need to warn any here not to infer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179768:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
from thence that I mean to favour Popery. I muſt confeſs to you, there are many of that Profeſsion, who having ſerved my Father and my Self very well, may fairly hope for ſome part in that Indulgence I would willingly afford to others who diſſent from Vs: But let me explain my Self, leſt ſome miſtake me herein, as I hear they did in my Declaration: I am far from meaning by this, a Toleration or qualifying them thereby to hold any Offices or places of Truſt in the Government; nay further, I deſire ſome Laws may be made to hinder the growth and progreſs of their Doctrine. I hope you have all ſo good an opinion of my Zeal for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, as I need not tell you I will not yield to any therein, not to the Biſhops themſelves, nor in my liking the Vniformity of it, as it is now eſtabliſhed, which being the Standard of Our Religion, muſt be kept pure and uncorrupted, free from all other mixtures; and yet if the diſſenters will demean themſelves peaceably and modeſtly under the Government, I could heartily wiſh I had ſuch a power of Indulgence, to uſe upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, as might not needleſly force them out of the Kingdom, or ſtaying here, give them cauſe to conſpire againſt the peace of it.</p>
            <p>My Lords and Gentlemen, It would look like flattery in Me to tell you to what degree I am confident of your wiſdom and affection in all things that relate to the greatneſs and proſperity of the Kingdom. If you conſider well what is beſt for Vs all, I dare ſay we ſhall not diſ-agree. I have no more to ſay to you at preſent, but once again to bid you heartily welcom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
